本期Primal Space视频由Squarespace赞助
This episode of Primal Space is supported by Squarespace.
前往squarespace.com/primalspace免费试用外加首单九折优惠
Get a free trial plus 10% off your first purchase by visiting squarespace.com/primalspace
从人类航天起步以来 已经有超过9000颗卫星发射入轨
Since the beginning of spaceflight, over 9,000 satellites have been launched into orbit.
但随着发射频率爆炸性提高 太空也变得越来越拥挤
But with the rate of launches increasing exponentially, space is about to get much busier.
原文应该有误
2016年NASA的报告中指出
大约有一亿块大于1毫米的太空垃圾
除了目前运行在地球轨道上的卫星 还有大约一亿块太空垃圾
In addition to every satellite currently in Earth's orbit, there is around 100,000 tonnes of debris
其中绝大多数都小到无法追踪
most of which is too small for us to track.
那么一个小小的物体可以给航天器带来多大危害呢？
But how much damage can a tiny object really do to a spacecraft?
我们又如何保护国际空间站免受其害呢？
And how do we shield the ISS from such dangers?
本期视频我们将了解物理计算后太空撞击的巨大威力
In this video, we're going to look at the powerful physics behind space impacts.
我们还将了解保护国际空间站的不同方法
We're also going to look at the different methods used to shield the ISS
以及我们如何在地球上测试这些防护措施
and how we put them to the test here on Earth.
这些飘荡在地球周围的垃圾中 我们只能追踪到比棒球大的
Out of all the objects hurtling around Earth, only those larger than a baseball can be tracked.
如果航天器的路径会与一块垃圾相撞
If a spacecraft is on a path to collide with a piece of debris,
那么它可以执行变轨来防止自己被击碎
it performs a maneuver to avoid being completely destroyed.
但对于数百万个无法追踪的微小物体 撞击的结果可能是灾难性的
But for the millions of tiny objects that can't be tracked, a collision could still be catastrophic.
原文有误 0.008J 是 8mJ 不是 0.8mJ
一滴0.2克的雨滴落在你头上的能量大约是8毫焦耳
A raindrop weighing 0.2 grams will fall on your head with about 0.8 millijoules of energy.
但同样的雨滴以太空垃圾的速度飞行就会有一百万倍的能量
But the same raindrop flying around as space debris would have over a million times more energy,
即使速度只快了1000倍
even though its speed is only 1000 times faster.
因为在动能的公式中 速度的影响更大
The reason that velocity makes such a difference here is because in the formula for kinetic energy,
质量是一次方 速度是二次方
mass is directly proportional but the velocity is squared.
科学家们肯定是明白这点的
This is obviously nothing new to scientists.
而到了真空的太空环境 这些微小的撞击是无法避免的
But when operating in the vacuum of space, these tiny impacts are unavoidable.
即使是极其微小的颗粒也会给航天飞机的风挡带来肉眼可见的撞击影响
Even things like flecks of paint have led to visible impacts on the windows of the Space Shuttle.
而来自地球轨道以外的微陨石
Micrometeoroids coming from outside of Earth's orbit
速度更是能达到每秒20公里
can be moving at even greater velocities like 20 kilometres a second.
所以足球场大小的国际空间站一直在暴露在太空垃圾的“火力”下
Since the ISS is the size of an entire football field, it is constantly in the firing line of debris.
航天员Chris Hadfield曾在太空
While onboard the space station,
拍下了这张某块太阳帆板上子弹孔大小的洞的照片
astronaut Chris Hadfield took this photo of one of the solar arrays with a bullet-sized hole right through it.
为了不使用笨重的防护板来保护像国际空间站这样大的航天器
In order to shield something as large as the ISS, rather than using heavy thick plating,
以其发明者 美国天文学家
弗雷德·惠普尔(Fred Whipple)的名字命名
人们转而使用的是“惠普尔屏蔽”
it uses something called a “whipple shield”.
结构是外层薄板 中层小空隙 内层厚板
This consists of a thin outer wall followed by a small gap and a thick inner wall.
外层材料不会吸收多少撞击的速度 但会把撞击物粉碎成大量细小碎片
The outer wall doesn't take much speed out of the impact but it shatters the projectile into much finer pieces.
让动能分散成在内层板上的大量更小的撞击
This means the kinetic energy is spread out into many smaller impacts on the inner wall.
在某些地方使用的屏蔽罩
In some areas of the shield,
中层的材料是耐冲击材料 比如凯夫拉纤维或氧化铝
the space between the two walls is stuffed with a high impact material such as kevlar or aluminium oxide.
在国际空间站上 有数百种不同的屏蔽配置
On the ISS, there are over a hundred different shield configurations,
又要在重量和防护等级中寻找平衡
as a balance needs to be found between the weight and the amount of protection.
幸运的是 我们可以在地球上很好地模拟并测试类似的撞击
Fortunately, we're able to do a great deal of testing on these types of impacts here on Earth.
普通的武器无法创造出轨道的速度
Since a typical firearm can't generate orbital velocities,
60年代的科学家发明了“轻气枪”
scientists back in the 60's invented something called the Light-Gas Gun.
尾部使用爆炸物推动活塞压缩密封腔内气体
This works by using an explosive charge to move a piston and compress a sealed chamber of gas.
腔体末端有一片爆破隔膜 会在特定压力下破裂
The end of the chamber has a thin bursting disk, scored with a cross which bursts at a specific pressure.
破裂后 迅速膨胀的气体会让物体加速到轨道速度
Once it bursts, the rapid expansion of gas accelerates the projectile up to orbital velocities.
这就是微小物体对一块铝撞击后的例子
This is an example of what a tiny object can do to a block of aluminum.
撞击的物体材质是聚碳酸酯 只有7克
The projectile in this experiment was made out of polycarbonate and weighed just 7 grams.
但当它以每秒7公里的速度撞击铝块时
But when it collided with the aluminum block at 7km/s,
却造成了自身尺寸五倍宽 五倍深的大坑
it carved out a crater 5 times wider and 5 times deeper than its own diameter.
这能让我们看到撞击的不同阶段 从而更好地了解太空中的撞击
To understand what goes on in orbital impacts, it helps to look at the impact in stages.
碎片撞击到物体时会很快减速下来
As the projectile collides with an object it decelerates extremely quickly,
让物体和碎片都被压缩
which compresses both the projectile and the object.
当两者的压力增加时
As the pressure of both objects increases,
温度也会高到熔化撞击区域 并汽化碎片
the temperature gets hot enough to melt the impact area and vaporize the projectile.
压缩的过程还会产生冲击波
The compression sends a shock wave through the object
足以摧毁整个这一部分的物质
with enough strength to completely tear apart the material.
这一切都在刹那间发生 国际空间站上的宇航员根本无从察觉
All of this happens in a fraction of a second, meaning astronauts onboard the ISS would never see it coming.
而现在研究又有了新的解决方案
But there is a new solution under research at the moment
可以为国际空间站带来更好的保护
that could provide even greater protection to the ISS.
目前惠普尔屏蔽的中层使用的是凯夫拉纤维或氧化铝
While current Whipple shields use kevlar or aluminium oxide between the walls,
这可以替换成一种全新材料 新材料有一种叫作“孔洞发生快速自愈”的性质
it's possible that this could be replaced with a new material that performs something called
Rapid Puncture-Initiated Healing.
具体是把惠普尔屏蔽的中层替换成一种液体
This involves replacing the filling of the Whipple shield with a liquid.
当碎片高速穿过屏蔽罩
As the debris passes through the shield at high velocity,
热量和摩擦会让液体流向孔洞 并在凝固时堵住孔洞
the heat and friction will stimulate the liquid to flow into the hole and plug it as it hardens.
在一次关于液体与氧气反应的测试中 孔洞在不到一秒内就被堵上了
One test involved the liquid reacting with oxygen, which sealed the hole in less than a second.
像这样的屏蔽层将会在未来 人类飞离可追踪的碎片的时候跟着持续发展进步
Shields like these will need to be constantly improved as we send humans beyond our field
of trackable space debris.
更轻更易替换的屏蔽层也会成为像飞往火星甚至更远的旅程中的关键部分
Lighter shields that are easier to fix will also be crucial for long haul trips to Mars and beyond.
当然 我们还要感谢地球上的大气层
Either way, we can be thankful that we have an atmosphere here on Earth
每天都在保护着我们
which protects us every single day.
使用Squarespace来为你的生意建设网站出奇的容易
Creating a website for your business with Squarespace is incredibly easy.
如果你是艺术家或者摄影师
If you are an artist or a photographer,
那么有一个网站能让人们瞻仰你的大作或者购买你的作品是很必要的
having an all-in-one place where people can admire and purchase your work is essential.
从大量预先设计好的模板中选择一个
Choose from a number of pre-designed templates
从而快速建立一个能展现你作品的专业网站
to quickly create a professional website that showcases your work.
有了Squarespace 你可以开网店
With Squarespace, you can set up an online store,
可以卖自己的作品 开始经营自己的生意
where you can sell your work and start growing your own business.
Squarespace还提供完整的数据分析 比如网页浏览量 访问来源 销量等等
Squarespace also provides you with full access to analytics like: page views, traffic sources, sales and more.
除了可以配置第三方域名
In addition to configuring third party domains,
客户还可以直接在Squarespace购买域名
customers can purchase domains directly from Squarespace.
如果你想建设自己的网站 那就前往squarespace.com免费体验吧
Head to squarespace.com for a free trial and when you're ready to launch your website,
前往squarespace.com/primalspace
go to squarespace.com/primalspace
并输入代码primalspace可获得第一个网站或域名的九折优惠
and add the code primalspace to save 10% off your first website or domain.
所以记得关注Primal Space频道
So make sure you're subscribed,
以便我们随时讨论 学习所有和太空有关的知识
so you can join in the discussion as we continue to learn more about all things space.
非常感谢大家的观看 我们下期视频见！
Thank you very much for watching and I'll see you in the next video!